I'm going to drop a small link in the chat
to get us kicked off with an activity.
And if you can't scan the code
so you can access the link in the chat,
or you can scan the QR code
on on my screen.
And what you'll see
is a page with two poems
and what I'll ask you to do,
I'll just give us, say,
30 40s of or so.
Just vote on one of the poems.
You can just click on them and then decide
which one of them you you like.
And so you'll probably see these two poems
on the theme of event.
And you can go ahead and invert.
Starting.
Cool.
Great. We have we have votes coming in.
Thank you everyone for playing along.
This was the first part of the activity.
The second part is I'm going to drop A
and B.
We're just going to name the poems A
and B, A for this one and D for this one.
I'm going to drop A and B in the chat.
So A and B and I'd love you
to put an emoji next
to a moji out, the one that you believe
was written by a human.
And so just hover over a in the chat
and then add a reaction of sorts.
Great. Awesome.
And as people
do so I'll just go ahead and read them.
Just the beginning at least.
So A is from the Greek veneer
event is less conquer than visitor,
yet also from the French and event
wind or breasts leaving a body in shock.
And so both a diplomatic mission
and a scandal
and the other one be the night
the lake gave back.
What we threw in keys, a ring,
the small dog of someone's grief.
We called it an event.
As if water could schedule its honesty.
I was nine, okay, awesome. So most.
I'm going to have to count the reactions
at one point, but I'm seeing I think more
people are voting for be as human.
Great.
I can't give you the answer
and this is not me being cheeky.
Instead, I want you to sit with that
feeling of not knowing whether
for the duration of this,
of this presentation,
whether the feeling of not knowing
whether A or B was written by a human.
It's a big part of what I'd love to share
today.
I've been doing something like we just did
for the last year and a half.
Now, as part of residencies
and collaborations,
I sat in a gallery
almost a year and a half ago now in Paris
as part of her residency,
and started the first version of this,
a model called coronation, which was fine
tuned on an anthology of English poetry
and then moved on to verses and heart.
Another version of this,
of this reinforcement
reverse, frontier, frontier and recover.
And the process is always the same.
So what's happening here
is I sit in the gallery for 30 minutes
and write a poem on a seam
that the room picks
so people can vote and choose themes.
I print mine and next to it I print one
that is written to the same theme
within three minutes,
within three seconds of sorts
by a model that I find tunes, right?
And at the end of the day,
I count the votes, people's votes.
People can vote with small neon stickers.
And then, depending on which model
wins and or loses, all of that data
is fed back into the model.
And the model is refined,
tuned based on that, on that input.
And so every one of these versions
that you just saw
effectively is based on the learnings
of the last model,
plus whatever the audience in the room
actually chose.
And given I have ten minutes,
I think I'll focus on on a few things.
So the big theme here,
if it's if I win, the model learns.
If it wins, I learn.
I commit to learning from the poems
basically that that are coming up.
And by the way, let's
see where where the votes landed.
Okay,
19 votes for this one and 15 for for this.
Soto. Thank you for voting.
I think that the three big, big words
that come to mind here is or rather,
the bigger theme is that the loss function
is a room of people in in in MML lingo.
But really the big themes on my mind
is when spectacle, the sort of reverse
ring test and undecidability
and on the point of spectacle,
obviously I'm in the room as a human
body and I am writing it's
a human against the machine.
One of us has to lose.
And I do think there's a part of me
that wants to just sit and reflect
or offer a provocation
around the narratives
that we've been handed around, how
in this confrontation and this encounter
with the machine, one of us needs
to destroy the opponent as an even.
Either we unplug the data center,
we end
up in a dystopian world, and there's a
there's an invitation of rethinking,
maybe this interaction
as one of two honorable warriors, or
a spectacle and a duel
where the two kind of honor each other
as part of this, this duel and this fight,
and you know that
that we can look at this and imagine this,
this moment as one spectacle.
Gladiator is not being maybe the best
example, but one, but one among others,
another one that there could be
love of sorts, that these, you know,
in, in my strange queer world,
that there could be
that these two fighters
could fall in love somehow,
and that their surrender in some way.
There's a case for surrender,
another feeling, another range of emotions
that could be explored
within, within that set, within that
30 minute set where someone is writing,
writing with the model.
The other
one is this idea of a reverse Turing test.
The touring old question pointed
that can the machine pass as a human?
And in this room it flips to some extent.
I am in a position where more and more
I've noticed that I will lose,
and between between one session
and another, I will take breaks.
I'll stand up, stand next to people
and look at what they're voting for,
and they'll look at me
and point at a poem and say, this is
AI, and sure enough, it will be mine,
which is a very strange feeling.
And then they'll vote for the other.
And so they're literally voting for AI.
And so I'm in a place where I'm feeling
humiliated that my poem is not.
I've been writing for such a long time,
and yet I am not passing the test.
And so from one session to another, I'm
in this position
where I need to effectively
almost tap into something more human in me
to be able to convince the audience
that no, no, no, I am.
I am the human.
My poems are worthy of your votes.
And so there's a point with
this humiliation also turns into humility.
I'm just learning one poem at a time.
And there's also this feeling of pride.
Sometimes the latest iteration of the
model is pretty good and winning a bunch.
And so I'm in this position, I'm like,
oh, this kiddo of mine,
I don't have kids, but oh wow, this,
this progeny of this machine,
progeny of sorts, is just like making it
into the world on its own.
And so it's just like this
very strange new range of emotions
coming up in this weird interaction
with this weird setup with the model.
And I do think there's a case as well
here for the
I'm bringing new poets,
other poets into into the fold.
So other poets than me are writing
and their poems are also being voted on.
And they feel it too, that there's,
there's almost like a chimeric.
Now, the model itself is almost feeding
on all of our poetries,
and it's almost becoming this game
era, this shared child of ours.
And then there's there's also this idea
that we are doing as part of all of this,
something that's very
we're creating a new topology
within the model, through people's
votes, through the different poets poems,
that there's almost like an artisanal,
artisanal reinforcement
learning using human feedback.
And this topology is our shared taste.
Somehow creating a new a new map
and a new topography,
which is which to me, makes me think of
a communal relative
to some extent artisanal RL, right?
Almost like a shared practice of feeding
and improving and teaching a model
altogether,
almost like a village raising a child.
And my last point
is about undecidability.
So this feeling that I that I started off
was, you don't know whether you voted
for a human or not.
And it brings me to this idea
that the truly the not knowing.
And there's this writing
about possible and whether
what is it to sit with
that feeling where we truly cannot know,
we cannot access it?
And I do think as I sit
with this performance, I continue
continue performing these spaces.
It almost feels like
that is the poem, right?
That the not knowing
is part of the is part and parcel of the
of the performance of this piece,
and that the poem is actually the
topography of this model that is emerging
and also the, the undecidability,
which one is human and which one is, is
not is also part of the poem.
And in that way it almost feels like that
is it's not something I've encountered
at other poems, almost like I do not know
who is who is the actual author here.
And that's there's something satisfying,
strangely satisfying about it.
It does invite this new relationship.
I feel there's a porosity
that is happening.
I am more porous to the model,
the more the models pores to me
and to the other poets
that are contributing.
And I'll show you, maybe in closing,
what's emerging from all of this.
And this is where you can learn
more about this piece.
You can actually chat
with the different models,
all of them,
and see how how they might evolve
and how they're seen, how they handle
a scene differently from one to the other.
This this is the actual data.
So I got really geeky in the last
couple of references about this,
just trying to capture what are the
what would be the classifiers, right,
based on people's
tastes and people's votes.
And I would love someone
to challenge me on all of this.
It's been kind of a solo act until now.
What are the the six emerging classifiers
from an evaluation point of view
that actually truly describe what the
what the audience has been voting for?
And these seven come up basically concrete
specificity versus abstract collage
all the way to earned metaphor versus
metaphor pileup.
And you can see here orange
means the model's winning frontier.
The latest model is is spilling out.
It is winning.
And this is a comparison
of all of the models
basically against these same classifiers.
Also the machine versus me.
And you can see here how the machine is
truly, you know, pushing pushing pushing.
It doesn't mean that
I've that I'm done for.
I am still fighting.
But but there has been a you know,
the tables have turned to some extent
and that in some ways
back to this feeling of surrender,
in this moment of learning,
that I do feel enriched by that.
Right.
Besides the pride that I'm behind,
I've thought this model
there isn't there's truly a new emotion
that that's just like worth
sitting with, that I am having to sit
with one one performance after another.
Yeah, that's that's it for me. Thank you.